The sixth day is over, you have now four more left to work and work very
seriously, very diligently, very patiently and persistently to get best
results of your stay here. Sixth day is a very important day. I am glad you
have crossed this hurdle, sixth day. As I said, the second day and the sixth day, it
is difficult for a weak-minded person to cross the hurdle. On the first day, even
when you start on upon, operation starts and with this operation, the second day
one feels like running away. Then again after Vipassana, the fifth day, sixth day,
operation goes deeper and one feels like running away under some pretext or the
other. One pretext. On the fifth day evening, the discourse says so much about
Dukkha, misery, misery. The birth starts with misery and then the whole life
misery, misery of disease, misery of old age, misery of dying, misery of things
happening which you don't like, misery of things not happening that you like,
misery, misery, life after life misery. Oh, this path is path of misery. One doesn't
want to understand. This is a very pessimistic teaching. No, I must run.
Doesn't try to understand or finds an excuse to run away. There is no pessimism,
not a trace of pessimism in the teaching. If the teaching said that you have to
suffer, there is misery, there is no way out, then yes, pessimism. But the teaching
says there's a way out. You can come out of all your miseries and you can reach
the stage where you are totally free from misery. Enjoy real peace, real harmony,
full of optimism, full of optimism. Back home in India there is a story, story in
our country. A mother sends the young son to the grocery shop nearby, gives one
empty bottle, one ten rupee currency note, go, go and buy some cooking oil. The boy
goes, goes, purchases oil, the oil bottle is filled with oil. On his way back, out
of carelessness, he gets knocked down. The bottle falls. Half of the oil flows
out. He picks up the bottle, half empty. Crying, crying, he comes to the mother,
oh mother, I lost half the oil. I lost half the oil. Very pessimistic, very
pessimistic. Story is story. Mother sends another son, another ten rupee note,
another bottle. He also buys oil, gets the bottle filled and story is story.
He also falls down. The bottle falls down. Half the oil has flowed out. This
boy picks up the bottle, very happy, smiling and goes to the mother, look I
saved half the oil. I saved half the oil. I fell down, the bottle fell down, the
bottle would have broken, all the oil would have gone away. Look, half the oil is
saved. Both have reached in the same situation, half bottle full, half empty.
One is crying for the empty one, very pessimistic. Other is happy with the
filled one, at least half is full. Very happy, optimistic. Story is story.
Mother sends the third son. And story is story. He also falls down. Half the bottle
is oil is out. He picks up the bottle like the second boy. He comes smiling. I
saved half the bottle. I saved half oil. But this boy is a Vipassana boy. Not only
optimistic, he is realistic also. I have lost half the oil. This is truth. My bottle
is half empty. And not only realistic, he is a workist like Vipassana. Now I must
work. He says I go out and work hard and by this evening I will earn five rupees
and get this bottle filled. Dhamma is not merely optimism, it is also realism, it is
also workism. So each individual has to work. Always remaining optimistic. Now
pessimism, not a trace of pessimism in Dhamma, all optimism, optimism. You got a
path now to come out of misery. Misery is there. You have to accept it. Half bottle is
empty. You have to accept it. How to fill it? The misery is there. Accept that misery.
And the way is there to come out of misery. Make use of that. This is what you
started doing. You are realizing the truth. It is not merely intellectual
exercise. Not an emotional or devotional acceptance of the truth of misery and
the way out of misery. You are experiencing. When you are working with
the sensation, you are living. Living wisdom is there. The truth is there which
you are experiencing. It is not the wisdom of somebody else. Not a borrowed
wisdom. Your own wisdom with direct experience. The whole process of
observing the sensation makes you understand. Because you started giving
importance to the truth within the framework of the body and the truth at
the experiential level. Otherwise whole life all importance was given to object
outside, object outside. You are craving. Even though you know you are craving. But
you are craving for object outside. And that object has become so predominant
for you. It keeps on overpowering you. You forget that you are craving. And you
also forget that by craving you have lost the balance of your life of your
mind. And you become very miserable. And you also don't understand that you have
become an addict to this craving. A natural requirement. You are thirsty. You
want water. Nothing wrong. You work hard to get water when you are thirsty. You
tried. You didn't get water. You smiled. All right. I try again. You didn't get. I
try again. You don't lose the balance of your mind. But when you start craving
water. Oh still not water. What will happen to me? I may die. Water. Water. You lost
the balance of your mind. You become so miserable. One is not observing all that
inside. Water is not that important. You are craving. Even craving is not that
important. Craving brings misery. The moment you start craving something that
means you are wanting something which is not there. You are not contented. You are
not satisfied with whatever is. You want something which is not. Which is not is
which is not. And you become very miserable because of that. You keep on
realizing this. Look I am becoming miserable. I am becoming miserable. Then
there is a way to come out of it. You don't know anything. You just go get
overpowered by this misery of craving. And then you don't know how you become
addicted to this craving. This becomes worse. One becomes addicted to craving.
When you start observing sensations a stage will come sooner. Maybe later in
some cases. When you start understanding that you are actually not craving for
this object or that object. You are craving for a particular sensation. When
you crave, crave for anything, a sensation arises. And when that craving is
fulfilled there is no more sensation. And you want that sensation again. So you have
to crave for something else. Once your craving is fulfilled, the object is
attained. It becomes still and you want something else. That is attained. Again
it becomes still. You want something else. You have become addicted to this craving.
Say somebody is living in a one-bedroom cottage. Quite happy. Suddenly it comes to
his mind. What one bedroom cottage? I must have at least a big house with three
bedrooms. Alright. Had a house with three bedrooms. Then it must be well furnished.
This furniture, that furniture. Well furnished. Alright. Well furnished. Then
that becomes still. Then I must have this apparatus, that apparatus. A TV and a
color TV and VCR and a definite deck or washing machine or cleaning
machine or this machine or that machine. The entire house is full of all these
things. No space even to breathe. And yet no satisfaction. Craving, craving. My car.
Oh this ordinary car, a tin pot. I must have that model. How about having a
Toyota? And then Toyota comes on. No, no. I must have BWM. And then no, no. I must
have Mercedes Benz. Oh no. I must have Rolls Royce. Oh no. And then not Rolls Royce
of this model or that model. Then latest model, latest model. Not just one, two. A
fleet of Rolls Royce. Still not contented. I must have my own helicopter.
People have their helicopters. I must have helicopter. Alright. Helicopter has
come. Then I must have my aeroplane. My own aeroplane. Aeroplane has come. Now I
want a spacecraft. I must go to the moon. A spacecraft to take me to the moon. Oh
that also is still. I must have a spacecraft to go to the Mars. To this
planet. To that planet. Not that. To this galaxy. That galaxy. Oh sky is the limit.
Even sky is not the limit. No limit. It is a bottomless bucket. You can't fill it.
Because you started getting addicted to craving. You are not craving for an
object. You are craving for the sake of craving. That makes the situation worse
and this is what happens. As you proceed on the path it will become so clear. When
we say somebody is addicted to alcohol or somebody is addicted to drugs. No. It's
wrong. At the surface level, apparent level, it seems to be so. Actually one is
addicted to the sensation. By taking alcohol one feels a kind of sensation and
one wants that sensation again and again. So one has to take alcohol again and
again. One has to take drug again and again. The sensation is so important.
This was the discovery of Buddha. Unless you start learning how to observe your
sensation you cannot come out of any addiction. Addiction of alcohol, addiction
of drug is nothing compared to your addiction of craving. Compared to your
addiction of aversion. So many impurities of the mind. You are addicted to all
those impurities and you keep on repeating them, repeating them, repeating
them because you are addicted to a particular type of sensation. You want
the sensation again and again. You generate certain impurities to get that
sensation. When that is over again you generate the same sensation by
generating this kind of negativity. This has become the habit pattern of the mind.
How to come out of it? Misery is there. But a way to come out of misery is also
there. Observe. Learn how to observe. Whatever is happening you are silent
witness. Don't react like somebody sitting at the bank of the river. The
flow of the river is there. You do nothing for the flow of the river. It's
natural. Sitting at the bank you just observe. This is more than that. A flow
of vibration, sensation throughout the body. You are feeling it. Like a research
scientist in his lab. In a glass tube some chemical is there. He heats up, heats
up some liquid chemical and that gets evaporated. Volatile matter gets
evaporated and that moves in some other tube, gets condensed, comes out as liquid.
He's just observing. Just observing. When it gets evaporated it doesn't start
crying, oh where my chemical went away. When comes back again as a liquid form
it will start dancing. He just understands. But all that understanding
of a scientist is only at the intellectual level. He's not experiencing.
Here you are experiencing the entire physical structure. What is this? How it
is working. The mental structure. The combination of the two. The interaction
of the two. How one is influencing the other. How one gets influenced by the
other. How the mind gets originated because of matter. How the matter gets
originated because of the mind. At times it looks as if matter is changing into
mind. At times it looks as if the mind is changing into matter. All that one is
experiencing and that makes so much difference. Then the wisdom that you get
by this experience is your own wisdom. Not because Buddha said so. Not because
your teacher says so. Not because any scripture says so. The material
structure made of subatomic particles, tiny little kalapas. The entire universe
made of tiny little kalapas. Four basic elements. Earth, water, fire, air and four
characteristic each of them. The entire universe is like that. Entire material
universe is like that. You see things solid. Earth element, liquid, water element.
Air, gaseous, air element and the temperature prevailing everywhere. Fire
element. The snow solid turns into water, gets evaporated as gas and there is
temperature in all the three cases. Similarly in our body also. Bones etc. so
solid. Earth element. Blood etc. water element. Gases etc. air element and the
temperature prevailing. Fire element. But that is not the deeper
level of the reality. The characteristic of each element which you experience at
the sensation level, this is more important. When you talk of earth element
not that you look for a particle of dust in this element. Nothing doing. Water
element. You don't look for a drop of water in it. Nothing doing. What is the
sensation that you feel because of that? Earth element. The entire field of
weight from the heaviest sensation feeling to the lightest is the
characteristic of the earth element. Like pulverized cement dust. Light. It
becomes solidified. Becomes heavy. When it is solidified it's rough. When it is
pulverized it is fine. Soft. You get sensations like that. Heavy, solidified
sensation of one type. Very rough. That gets dissolved and then you have soft.
Same earth element but very soft. All the field of weight is the characteristic of
the earth element. Similarly the entire field of movement from the little
little movement to very big movement is the element of air. The entire field of
temperature from the coldest to the hottest is the field of fire element.
And the water element. Binding nature. Cohesiveness. The entire structure is
within your boundary. It's bound up. This is water element. This is what you
experience. All the sensations that you have been experiencing till now and the
all the experiences that you will experience in future you have only these
four elements manifesting with this sensation or that sensation. At times
masses of subatomic particles will arise with the predominance of earth element
or with the predominance of water element or with the predominance of air
element or with the predominance of fire element. That's all. These four elements
are there. A good meditator will not get affected. Oh now masses of kalapas have
arisen with earth element. Predominance of earth element. Let me see how long
they last. Fire element. Let me see how long they last. Water element. Let me see
how long they last. Air element. Let me see how long they last. It does not react.
One just observes. And these sensations which are manifestation of different
elements they arise. Sooner or later they pass away. They arise. Sooner or later they
pass away. It becomes clearer. Clearer. Like a scientist you are exploring the
truth the nature of these kalapas and you are also exploring the truth of
your mind. How the mind gets influenced. How you understand how these kalapas
get originated. How they multiply. How the mind gets influenced by them and how
you react and the reaction gets multiplied. All that phenomena becomes so
clear. So clear. These kalapas, subatomic particles, how they arise, how they get
originated. Four kinds of food you give to them. Two material food and two mental
food. Material input and mental input are responsible for the generation of
different types of kalapas in your body. And that you will start experiencing as
you proceed on the path it will become clearer and clearer. The material food.
The food that you take once, twice or three times during the day. What type of
material food you have taken. That type of kalapas will start arising with the
predominance of this element or that element. For example as you proceed on
the path and you become more and more sensitive to your sensations it will
become very clear. Say one day you have taken real hot food. Indian hot food. Lot
of chilies. And then you sit for meditation after some time. And you get a
burning sensation here and a burning sensation here. The fire element. You are
given that input and the fire element. The atoms are arising with the
predominance of fire element. You have taken very stale food or very greasy food and
you sit for meditation. Earth element. You feel so heavy. So heavy here. So what type
of food you are taking. You take healthy food your body becomes healthy. You take
unhealthy food your body becomes unhealthy. Law of nature. Second input. The
material input of the atmosphere around you. Every moment the body keeps on
sucking the material atmosphere around. One lives in a cold country, cold climate.
One type of body lives in hot country, hot climate. Another type of body. This
kind of kalapas get generated because of the atmosphere around. Two other inputs.
Mental inputs. The present mind at this moment my mind is generating this
particular sankhara. This sankhara, this type with this sankhara, this mind with
this sankhara will start generating these atomic kalapas particles with
particular type of element. Like at this moment I generate anger. I have generated
anger at the mental level but the kalapas that have started generating are
kalapas with the predominance of fire burning, burning, burning. Or I generate a
fear, fear sankhara and then trembling, trembling, air element, air element. What
type of input I am giving at the mental level at this moment. How the mind turns
into matter or influences the matter or makes the matter to originate in a
particular way. And then the fourth input is your old sankharas. The reality
of the mind is every moment it is influenced by the sankhara. The present
sankhara either you keep on generating sankhara from moment to moment. You stop
generating sankhara as you practice in vipassana. You don't generate any sankhara
at this moment. Then your old stop will start coming up on the surface. This is
the fruit of your old sankhara. In your daily life also as you get established
in the technique it will be very clear. You get something unpleasant happens in
your life. Before that something unpleasant happens in the life outside
very unpleasant sensation has started in you. And then only something
unpleasant happens in the life. Something very pleasant happens in the
life a pleasant sensation has started in you. So the fruit first comes as a
sensation. The seed was planted as a sensation. Say a seed of anger. My
sankhara of anger as I plant the seed of anger I feel so much heat. Fruit of this
particular sankhara when it comes up it will come up with the same kind of
sensation again heat very much heat. So the sankhara that I am generating now is
one input and it creates fire element in the body. And the sankhara of the past if
it is a sankhara of anger the fruit of that will again have fire element. Like
this the sankhara now or the sankhara past are another two reasons for
different kind of kalapas to arise different kind of kalapas to arise. As
you keep on observing then you understand that more and more I react to
these sensations more and more I generate new sankharas and I create more
and more misery for me. And if I stop generating new sankharas then the old
ones come on the surface they create a sensation and again I smile at the
sensation. This is also impermanent. Let me see how long it lasts. Let me see how
long it lasts. It passes away. That means layers of that particular old sankhara
has come on the surface and passed away. Chunks after chunks will come on the
surface and pass away. You are relieved from that. You are not generating a new
sankhara. You are getting liberated from your old stock of the sankharas and the
process is such it will take take you to the stage. Everyone who keeps on working
working properly of course it takes time. Not that one becomes perfect by taking a
10-day course but by 10-day course one understand this is how I have to work
and one keeps on working keeps on working ultimately one reaches the stage
where there is no more past sankharas left and you don't generate a new
sankhara and this is what is called Kheenam Puranam Navam Natya Sambhavam
Kheenam Puranam. All the old stock is eradicated now and no new sankhara can
be generated. One is a liberated person and this happens by one's own practice.
No one else can do that for you. The sankharas that is accumulated is
accumulation of your own. You have accumulated them. You are responsible for
that. Your ignorance is responsible for that. Slowly you are coming out of that
ignorance. You are developing your wisdom, living wisdom, wisdom at the
experiential level and you see how the old stock is getting eradicated,
eradicated. You are coming nearer and nearer to the final goal. Each individual
has to work. No one else can do anything for you. Can only just show the path.
Hindrances are there. Difficulties are there. In the language of those days it
is called Nivarana, like curtain, thick curtains which won't allow you to see
the things behind the curtain. You can't see the reality within you because
of these Nivaranas, these obstacles, these barriers. Five big Nivaranas, five
big barriers. I call them five big enemies of every meditation, Vipassana
meditator. Five big enemies. Two big enemies, craving and aversion. You are
meditating to come out of your old habit of craving, to come out of your old habit
of aversion. And ignorantly you are meditating. You are meditating and
multiplying your craving. You are meditating and multiplying your aversion.
You are supposed to come out of craving. You are supposed to come out of
misery, of craving. You are supposed to come out of the misery of aversion and
look what you started doing. This is because of the old habit pattern of the
mind, because of the ignorance, because of these Nivaranas, these two Nivaranas,
two barriers. An example how it happens. In a course like this there are many
reasons for asking the students, no communication, don't talk with the fellow
student. If any problem come and discuss with the assistant teacher or the
teacher. But keep on working your own. Keep on working your own. But human mind
is human mind. Always inquisitive about others. You get one opportunity and you
start talking, hey how about you? How about you? And this person replies, I get a
flow of tingling vibrations. Tingling throughout the body? And I didn't get any
tingling? And somebody says I got a flow of like electric current throughout the
body. Electric current? Wonderful. I didn't get. And when you sit for meditation now,
I want tingling sensation. I want electric current or no electric current
for me. No tingling sensation for me. And you keep craving, craving, craving. You were
here to come out of craving. And in the name of meditation, in the name of
Ippassana, I started craving, craving. Craving is craving. Misery. Even if you
crave for the final goal, liberation, Nirvana. I want Nibbana, I want Nibbana.
You are running in the opposite direction of Nibbana. Nibbana is a stage
free from craving. And you are multiplying your craving. How can you
reach the stage of free from craving by generating craving? Not possible. So
whenever you find this enemy is overpowering you, come out of it as
quickly as possible. Don't allow it. Whatever comes about this moment, this
sensation or that sensation, even no sensation, doesn't matter. You accept the
reality of this moment as it is, as it is. What is not there, you want that. Then
again, the same old habit pattern, what is not there, you want that. And that
becomes craving. And you start having attachment to this craving. It becomes a
big misery for you. Similarly, aversion. An example, you are made to sit for one
hour, Adikthana. You can't open your eyes, can't open your legs, you can't open
your hands. You somehow manage half an hour. You manage 45 minutes. After that,
then the torture starts. Then again, the same human mind inquisitiveness about
others. You are not supposed to open your eyes. And still you open a little bit of
eye. What is happening to others? Is this pain, I am only suffering with pain or
everybody is suffering with pain? You are so curious about others. And you notice at that
time everybody is sitting like a statue of Buddha. That means they have got no pain.
Only I have got pain. My pain has not gone away. Everybody's pain has gone away. Oh this
pain. Then your aversion becomes multiply. Aversion towards this pain. My teacher
keeps on saying everything is anicca, anicca, impermanent, impermanent. Maybe
true. But this pain is permanent. This is not impermanent. Look, how many times I
told you, you are anicca, you are anicca. And still it is not going. This is
permanent. This is permanent. Aversion, aversion, aversion. The enemy has overpowered
you. You are multiplying aversion. You are here to come out of aversion and you
started multiplying the aversion. Another two big enemies. Understand all these
enemies, they are defilements, mental defilements, which came in your body, in
your mind as guests and then they became owner of the house. They don't want to go
out. And when you practice vipashyana they can't stay, they have to go out. Like
a switch on light comes on the darkness has to go. You won't have to tell darkness
who you go away now. Now there is light. When you practice vipashyana these
defilements have to go and they don't want to go. So they give a kick from
within. Stop vipashyana. This is not good for me. I don't want to go. You stop vipashyana.
Two kinds of kicks are given from within. One big kick is that it will make you
so drowsy. You have a sound sleep all right. You sit for meditation you feel so
drowsy, so drowsy. A very big enemy is overpowering you. Fight it out. Have
heart breathing. If that doesn't work and if it is not that one hour sitting,
stand up and meditate with heart breathing. That doesn't work. Get out, walk
five minutes or ten minutes, observe your sensation or respiration, come and
sit. Keep on fighting this enemy. Otherwise this enemy overpowers you. You
can't meditate. Another kick from within. Either this kick will make you very much
drowsy or it will make you very much agitated. You feel like doing little bit
of this, feel like doing little bit of this, little bit of this, little bit of
this, but no meditation. You are in one hour sitting Adikthana and a kick from
within. You have taken whole of your body outside and then you realize oh I was in
Adikthana. How I came here? A kick from within won't allow you to practice
properly. This enemy, dangerous enemy. Another enemy, fifth enemy. Doubt, doubt.
All kinds of doubt come in the mind. What is this technique? What sort of
technique is this? Observe respiration, observe respiration. Even when I was not
observing respiration, it was there all the time. What I gained by observing
respiration? Now observing the heat, observing the perspiration. What I'm
doing? Have I gone crazy? What kind of meditation? And this doubt will not
allow you to work. Another doubt at times, another doubt comes about your teacher.
What teacher? I was expecting a great guru from India with capital G. What kind
of guru? He doesn't have matted long hair, does not have big mustache or
beards, even no shaven head and he has got no bunches of rosaries around his
neck, no trademark on his forehead, no paraphernalia of a teacher, no guru. What
kind of guru? He doesn't look like freak. He looks like a straight. What guru? No. And he's got no
supernatural power. He can't fly in the air. He can't dig dips in the earth. He and his
assistant keep on asking, how about you? They should know what, how about you? Why
they ask a student? No supernatural power. Doubt. Doubt and you can't work. Third
kind of doubts come. Yes, the technique is good because so many people keep
coming and they get benefit. They keep coming repeatedly. Certainly it is good.
Teacher is also good because so many people listen to him. So perhaps good.
Alright. I am not good. I am not fit for this. Doubt about one's own capability. I
am not fit. This is not the time for me. And this scene is not for me. I better
quit. And one feels like running away. Oh this doubt, doubt, doubt. Any of these
three doubts overpowers you and you stop meditating. These five nirvanas, five
enemies, be careful. Don't allow them to overpower you and then you will find
you are progressing, you are progressing, you are progressing.
The technique is wonderful. There is no dogma involved in it. No blind faith
involved in it. No cult involved in it. It's pure science of mind and matter. The
interaction of mind and matter. How out of ignorance this mind keeps on reacting
to these sensations. Keep on generating negativities and because of this
negativity more and more this particular type of sensation arises and when that
sensation rises you more react with negativity and this vicious circle
becomes miserable, more and more miserable. You start observing it. You
start coming out of it. Just universal law of nature. Nothing to do with this
particular organized religion or that organized religion. Truth is truth.
Universal truth. Universal law. Dhamma is universal law. Natural law. And that will
become clearer and clearer if you keep on working. The law of nature is such
that if you keep on reacting with negativity you are multiplying your
misery. You stop this reaction you started coming out of misery and this
has worked even in the past. This works now. This will keep on working in future.
Even in the past whether there was a Buddha or no Buddha. Buddha says whether
I am there or not. Whether somebody becomes an enlightened or not. The law of
nature remains the same. It is eternal. All the time when one generates
negativity one is bound to suffer. All the time one starts coming out of
negativity one starts getting liberated from the misery. A Buddha discovers. This
law remains covered. People do not know what is happening. Deep inside how you
generate negativity people do not know. The enlightened one's enlightenment is
that he goes deep inside and finds out how one keeps on generating negativities
to these sensations and keeps on multiplying one's misery. How observing
the sensation one can come out of this misery. Come out of the negativity. This
is found out by somebody which is there already. The law is there already. And then
out of compassion he starts teaching it to others. Giving this technique to
others. People follow it and they come out of their misery. This happened to
thousands upon thousands of people in the life of the Buddha. And after that
also during these 25 centuries whoever practiced got the same benefit. And even
in future who will be practicing will get the same benefit. Today anybody is
practicing will get the same benefit. The law is law. It is eternal. The same law.
The Dharma is eternal. The same law prevails. At the time of Buddha
how miserable people came out of their misery. Not because of any miracle or
magic of Buddha. The same technique was given. One instance of this person
Angulimal. A young man very angry. He had taken a vow that he will kill
1,000 human beings. How much anger he has got. And he killed 999 of them and he
was looking for the thousandth one. And how to remember how many he has killed.
So whomever he kills he cuts the finger and puts a garland around his neck.
And keeps on counting how many fingers. And that is why he was called Angulimal.
One he is wearing a garland of fingers. When he was looking for the one
thousandth person he came across Buddha. Or rather Buddha out of compassion came
to him. Just to save him from his misery. No magic. No miracle. Same technique was
given to him. And he started realizing that he is a miserable person. Full of
misery. And started working on it. And working, working, working he came out of
misery. Here is the final goal. A full liberated person. An anaharanth. Full of
compassion. Full of love. Full of goodwill for others. And now he goes
around from village to village. From countryside to countryside. From city to
city. Everywhere people are so miserable. I was so ignorant. Out of my ignorance I
had been harming myself. I had been harming others. Like me there are so many
who are harming themselves. They are harming others. If they get this wonderful
technique certainly they will come out of their misery. Certainly they will come
out of their misery. So out of compassion he goes to different places.
He teaches this dhamma, this technique to others. Some people recognize him.
Although he's become a monk now. He's the same Angulimala who has killed my mother
or killed my father or killed my wife or killed my husband or killed my son. Same
Angulimala. And out of anger they throw stones at him. They beat him. Blood starts
flowing from his body. But from the heart only compassion flows. Oh miserable
people. I was also equally miserable. Out of ignorance I was harming myself. I was
harming others. See this technique how it helps you. You will come out of all your
misery. Give it trial. Give it trial. Full of compassion. The whole life full of
compassion. How miserable people came out of their misery so easily. Of course by
practicing the technique understanding that this technique alone can take us
out from the misery. Unless we come out of our negativities, unless we come out
of our sankaras, there is no liberation from misery. A very miserable woman by
the name of Kisa Gautami got married and for number of years had no issue and she
was craving for a child. After a number of years she got a child. Unfortunately
within two years the child died. She had developed so much of attachment to the
child and the child died. This sorrow was unbearable for her. She took the dead
body corpse of the child to the breast and she won't give it to the people to
take to the cremation ground or take to the graveyard. No my child does not die.
It is sleeping. Please do something so that he gets awakened. Please do
something. And people say no mother he has died and no use expecting that he
will wake up. But she has gone totally insane. No I can't give. My son has
not died. Has not died. Please do something. Please do something. One wise
person told her nobody has got any medicine for this dead body. You may go
to Buddha. He has got his meditation center here. You go there. Perhaps he may
do something for you. And she went to Buddha. Placed the dead body before his
feet and crying crying my son has not died. People say he's dead. Even if he's
dead please do something. Please do something. Buddha found that her mind
was so emotionally unbalanced any kind of dhamma teaching will not work there.
He had his own way of teaching. Asked her all right. Go to the city. Get a few grains
of sesame. Very happy. Buddha is going to do something for my son. Buddha said
wait. Listen the instruction properly. You must bring these seeds of sesame from
some house where nobody has died. From a family where nobody has died. Yes, yes
sir. I'll bring that. And she went out. From house to house. From street to street.
Every house she's asking for sesame seed. My son has died and Buddha is going to
do something. Please get give me. Oh you may take bag full of seed. May your son
get alive. And then she questions has anybody died in your family. And with a
long face she says yes my father has died or my mother has died or my brother has
died or so and so has died. And the next house and the next house. Not a single
house she got where somebody has not died. And by the time the whole day she
came to senses. There is no house. There is no family where somebody does not die.
This is law of nature. People take birth to die sooner or later. And now her mind
was in a position to learn dhamma. She came back and Buddha gave dhamma. The
same dhamma. Observe respiration. Observe sensation. Go deeper, deeper, deeper. And
you find all your misery will get evaporated layers after layers. And this
Kisa Gautami became an arhan. Fully liberated. And all her life serving
people like me. So many mothers. Like me so many sisters. Oh they are so miserable.
If they get this wonderful dhamma they will come out of their misery. Out of
this compassion kept on serving people in dhamma. Kept on serving people in
dhamma. Another miserable person like this. Daughter of a very rich person
Patachara. She also lost her husband. She had two sons. Lost both the sons. Lost her
brother, mother, father. Now nobody was there in the wide world. And she became
insane. Total insane. Running in the streets of Savati. Totally naked. And
people throwing stones at her. And she won't understand what is happening.
Because of some past parmi, some good karmas of the past. She came in contact
with Buddha. Buddha was teaching dhamma to others. And she passed by. And Buddha
said come my child. And she came there. And as she sat down she got senses even
for a few minutes. And she found that she is naked. Somebody threw a cloth over her.
And from then onwards she was called Patachara. Her name was Patachara. Buddha
gave dhamma. The same technique. And working on it, working on it, she came out of
all her miseries. If Buddha had used some miraculous powers to give life to
the son of Kisa Gautami. Or give life to the sons of this Patachara. Or the
husband of Patachara. Or the mother, father, brother of Patachara. Then Buddha
would not have been Buddha. Give dhamma. This is a temporary relief. Even if
somebody gets life again. It's a temporary relief. Misery is there all the time. One
starts understanding as one progresses on the path. A time comes. One can
remember the past. Lives after lives. And Buddha says you just see. Lives after
lives. Countless lives. How many of your relatives, your dear ones have passed
away. They have died. If you just accumulate the bones of all those who
have died in the past and you accumulate it will be like a huge mountain. And the
tears that you have shed with every dear one who has died. If you accumulate all
those tears it will be like a huge ocean. You want to carry on the same thing in
future also. Life after life. Countless life in future. Again rolling in misery.
Come out of it. Here is a way. Here is a technique. N of you, N of you have suffered so
much. Come out of it now. Come out of it. And he gives this technique. Which is just
law of nature. Everybody works on it. Whoever works comes out of it. And it is
not necessary also that to work on this technique one must come out of the
householder's life. One should become a monk or a nun. Well if one becomes a monk
or a nun there are less responsibilities of the worldly life. And one can work,
give full time to this. The work becomes easier. But this is not absolutely
essential. Dhammaiswar is for everyone. A recluse, a monk, a nun or a householder.
Householder may have difficulties because of so many responsibilities. But
still the path is the same for both. Hardly there were hundred thousand monks or
nuns with him. And rest of them, millions of them in northern India.
Practicing vipashna and coming out of their misery. Practicing vipashna coming
out of their misery. An incident of a very rich person. A multimillionaire of
those days. Anath Pandika. He used to give lot of dana. Lot of dana. Because
tradition is such that a householder must give dana. If one does not give
dana then there is more of ego. As a householder one is not supposed to beg
food from others. For a monk it is alright. For a nun it is alright. As a
householder one has to earn money properly, honestly, hard-workingly. But
when you start earning money then the madness comes. I am so smart. I am so
intelligent and that is why I am earning so much money. This ego. One starts
living a ego-centered life. A self-centered life and starts hating
everybody else. Oh these people. Ignorant people. They are not intelligent. They are
not smart. That's why they are not hard-working. That's why they are not
earning. And I look I am so smart. I am so intelligent. I am so hard-working. This
ego comes which is dangerous. The whole purpose of giving dana was to come out
of the ego. And the same dana makes one ego-centered person. One has lost dhamma.
One doesn't know what for I am giving dana. This person was giving a lot of
dana. This title Anatha Pindaka. Anath means orphans. Those who are very poor.
Pindaka. One who gives them food. That was his title because he was giving so
much food to all hungry people. He had branches of his business throughout
India and beyond India in different countries. And this was a rule that
wherever his office or branch is there nobody should remain go hungry there.
People should get food. But still he didn't know dhamma. Came in contact with
Buddha. That means came in contact with dhamma. Got vipassana. Practicing
practicing. Purified the mind. Purified the mind. Got the first dip of Nibbani
stage. Changed person altogether. Now he was a changed person altogether. Now
giving donation is not to build ego. It's to deflate ego. It's to dissolve ego.
All this money that has come to me it is because of my past good karmas it has
come to me. It must be used for the good of others. Of course as a householder I
must make use of it for my own maintenance. For the maintenance of all
those who are depending on me. But the rest of it must go for the good of
others. For the good of others. And now he understands the good of others which
is the real good of others. I give food to a hungry person. I must give. It's
alright. But next day again this person is hungry. I give water to a thirsty
person. After some time again he may become thirsty. I give some medicine to a
sick person. He may get another disease or the same disease may come up again. I
may give clothes to a naked person. After some time the clothes get worn, torn and
again he's naked. I'm not taking out, I'm not helping people to come out of all
their miseries if they get dhamma. If they get this wonderful technique of
vipassana. Oh they come out of their misery. Total liberation from misery.
Misery that they were encountering from life after life, life after life. They
will come out of it. Dhamma should go to each and every suffering person. Besides
all the time giving material dana, this dana is most important.
sabba dhanam dhamma dhanam janati. The dana of dhamma is the highest dana. And he
goes to Buddha. Buddha at that time was living in Rajgiri.
Please respect to him and tell sir. Why not come to Savasthi? He was living in
Savasthi which was the most populated city of India of those days. Most
populated city. Large number of people are miserable. All miserable. Rich or
poor. If you have a meditation center there so many people will get benefit.
Sir please do something. Come there. Buddha smiled. So he understood that
Buddha has agreed. He came back home looking for a center. A place where Buddha
can start teaching dhamma to people. Meditation center should not be in the
midst of the city with so much of noise and all. It should not be very far away
where people cannot go. So looking for a proper place. Peaceful and yet not very
far away from the city. He came across, came across a garden. A park. Very calm.
Very quiet. Congenial for meditation. And he inquired who is the owner of this
park. And he came to know that the prince, the son of the king is the owner.
Prince Jetav. And he went to him. Sir I want to buy your park. And the prince
became very angry. I am not here to sell my park. This is for my own amusement. I
can't sell it. No sir I have to buy. Any price. Just to get rid of him. The prince
says you know the price of this land. You have to spread gold sovereigns. The
entire land. This is the price. The deal is done. I will spread sovereigns.
Cart loads of sovereigns he is bringing and spreading. The prince says have you
gone mad? No land can be that valuable. What are you doing? Are you a mad
person? He says no I am not mad. This land is going to become so valuable. Buddha is
going to come here and teach wonderful vipashana. And all my wealth is nothing
compared to one person getting vipashana. Even one person comes out of
the misery. My wealth is nothing compared to that. And I know not one person.
Thousands upon thousands will get benefit. And immediately meditation center
where 10,000 people can live, stay, meditate, learn dhamma. This volition to
serve others. Dana was there even previously. Now the Dana is how more and
more people will get benefited. Not to inflate his ego. To deflate his ego.
Dissolve the ego. Just to serve others. This multimillionaire it so
happened that due to some karmas of the past he became a pauper for a short
period. He had no money. He is a pauper. And when he was a money person he will
come to the center every day morning and evening to meditate. And as a
householder he understands I should not go to the center empty handed. I must
carry something for the meditators. And every time he comes he brings something
for the meditators. Now he's a pauper. He's got nothing to bring. And then
something comes in his mind. Behind his house he's got a small garden. And in
that garden he has accumulated very good fertile soil from different parts of
India. Now he takes two handful of that earth. Fertile earth. Comes to the center.
Under a tree. At the root of the tree. May this tree grow. Under the shade of this
tree. May someone get dhamma. May someone get meditation. Volition is there. Whether
handful of earth or millions of rupees makes no difference. Volition. It is the
volition that counts. After some time again he became multimillionaire.
Started giving the donation in the same way. He understands dhamma now. That
whatever I give the amount is a material. My volition. My dhamma volition for the
good of others. For the benefit of others. Not expecting anything in return.
When one does not know dhamma. Then one keeps on giving dana but inflating the
ego. One builds a big hospital. A school. A college. But wants it to be named a
Goinka hospital. A Goinka school. A Goinka college. And this name must be
written in golden letters at the gate. Goinka school. Goinka college. Madness. One
doesn't know what one is doing. The whole volition is wrong. Understanding of
dhamma is wrong. The volition is to give without expecting anything in return. To
give for the benefit of others. For the benefit of others. How people started
changing. Changing in their life. Different people. Householders. One mother
Visakhha. Again a daughter of a very rich person. Married to another rich person but
the family had no dhamma at all. And how very wisely she turns the entire
atmosphere of this family where there was no dhamma. How everybody became a good
meditator and changed the whole attitude of the family. And the whole family
became full of peace, harmony. Where there was so much of tension and misery. How
dhamma starts working. Brings peace for one and all. And this was not merely at
the time of Udthar. It kept on. Whoever worked. Whenever one worked the same
result comes. One incident in the life of my teacher C.R.G. Ubakhine when
Burma became independent. There were small small states, princely states. And a
person, a good politician, statesman, he amalgamated all these states and made a
union of Burma. And to satisfy these princes one of their leader was made the
president of the country of the union of Burma. Now president has got no power
according to the Constitution there. The prime minister has all the powers. And yet
this person becomes so happy that I am now the president of the union of Burma.
Previously I was just a ruler of a small small place. Very happy. One evening he
gives a big party. All the diplomats and the elite of the of the city they all
come there. A big party. 7.30 is the time to start the party. Everybody has come.
All the guests have come. The host is not to be seen. 7.45 the host is not to be
seen. 8 o'clock the host is not coming. Prime minister got worried. What's going
on? He sent somebody to the residence in the first floor. And those who went up
there came back and told him sir he can't come. Why? What happened? He has
drank so much. He's unconscious lying on the floor. He can't come. Oh but without
the host how can this party this is president's party. Conscious or
unconscious? Bring him somehow. Let us start the party. And two of them helped
him to come. Half conscious half unconscious hiccuping hiccuping and he
comes. He's made to sit on the main chair and the course and the dinner starts.
First course is served. Second course is served. When the third course was being
served he started vomiting. Vomiting. Prime minister was so unhappy. We call
our land a Dhamma land. Our government a Dhamma government. And what sort of
president we have got? What could be done? Next day when he came to census he
telephoned to prime minister. If you want I will resign. But I cannot come out of
alcohol. It is impossible. In our royal tradition when the heir to the throne is
born that means the first son to the king is born then the first input given
is the best quality alcohol. In a silver spoon or a gold spoon. This was my first
input sir. And since then I'm taking alcohol alcohol. Half of my blood has
become alcohol. I can't come out can't come out of alcohol. Now this person
fortunate because of some good parmi of the past. One day he passes in front of
the teachers. Just out of inquisitiveness enters there. And
that was the day the tenth day the last day and he sees everybody's face blooming
with operation is over now. And bomb is given on the wounds. Everybody smiling
smiling. Hey what's going on here? Meditation is taught. What meditation?
Anapana is taught. Vipassana is taught. Being a born Buddhist he has been reading
about this Anapana and Vipassana in the scriptures but he never knew that
anybody is teaching this and such results are coming. Everybody says we
feel so peaceful so harmonious. I had no peace in my life. I never know what
harmony is. I'm such an agitated person. Sir can I come can I come also join? Yes
yes. Whether a prince or a pauper anybody everybody can come and meditate.
What shall I have to do? You have to take five precepts. Five precepts? Oh no no no
four precepts. Fifth one is out of question I can't do. Then go away we
can't take you. And he wants this peace and he's not taken. So he starts arguing
starts bargaining. One little peg sir every day very little. No nothing
doing. One peg after alternative days nothing doing. One in five days nothing
doing. Go away we can't teach you unless you have got this foundation strong. This
five sila are foundation of meditation. And then he says all right then somehow
I will control myself but sir under one condition that when I go back home you
should not stop me from drinking. How can I stop you going back home? You are your
own master. You drink as much as you like. But here no I would recommend you
going back home you should not drink. But if you drink how can I stop you? But
these ten days no drink. All right sir I want peace. I want harmony. And he
practiced the same practice. After ten days he goes to the president house his
own house there. And somebody is drinking even hundred yards away. He says
drinking. Who is drinking here? He can't bear. He can't bear others drinking out of
question for him to drink. And the whole ten days nobody told him if you go back
home and drink you will get this hell or that hell nothing doing. In Dhamma there
is no threatening. What happens? What is drink? He is addicted to the sensation of
the drink. And when he learned how to observe the sensation observe the
sensation all the sankharas of the alcohol had gone away. The addiction of
alcohol was gone away. How can he drink now? If this has happened only to one
president of the Union of Burma perhaps there was some miracle involved. This
happens to thousands of people coming to courses. Addict to alcohol. Addict to
drug. Addict to this or more than that. Addict to craving. Addict to aversion.
Addict to fear. Addict to depression. All these mental illnesses how they go away
easily. Dhamma is so wonderful. Dhamma is so scientific. Dhamma is so non-sectarian.
Dhamma is so universal. Dhamma is so result oriented. It gives you result here and
now in this very life. Good that you have joined the course. Make best use of the
remaining four days. They are wonderful days of your life. At least get
established in the technique. How to practice it? It's a lifetime job. You have
to work for the whole life but get established in the technique. Make use of
the time. Make use of the opportunity. Make use of the facility. Make use of this
wonderful Dhamma. The wonderful technique. To come out of the bondage of all the
cravings, aversions, illusions, delusions. To enjoy real peace, real harmony, real
happiness. May all of you enjoy real peace, real harmony, real happiness.
Hmm. Take rest for about five minutes and then again start working. Take rest for
five minutes.